Stephen Jay Gould Papers, 1899-2004
Stanford University Libraries.
- Series 19. Biographical
  - Gould's business cards (Box 684, Folder 12)
  - Gould's I.D. cards (Box 684, Folder 13)
  - Gould's passports (Box 684, Folder 14)
  - Interview transcript: Gould and Kayzer (Box 684, Folder 15)
  - Interview transcript: Gould and Lewontin (Box 684, Folder 16)
  - A Yankee Fan Surviving in Boston, from The Yankee Observer, 1992 (Box 684, Folder 17)
  - An Interview with Stephen Jay Gould (Box 684, Folder 18)
  - Interview transcript: An Interview with Stephen J. Gould on June 24, 1992, by William Glen, 1992 Jun 24 (Box 684, Folder 19)
  - Interview with Stephen Jay Gould, from The Skeptic (Box 684, Folder 20)
  - Origines de L'homme [Interview with Gould] (Box 684, Folder 21)
  - Polymath Predictions: An Interview with Stephen Jay Gould (Box 684, Folder 22)
  - Roots Writ Large (Box 684, Folder 23)
  - The Spice of Life (An Interview with Stephen Jay Gould) (Box 685, Folder 1)
  - Stephen Jay Gould, an Illustration, Victor Ichioka and An Interview with Stephen Jay Gould: This View of Writing, Jared Haynes, 1991 (Box 685, Folder 2)
  - Obituaries (5 folders)
  - Memorial Service Program, Harvard, 2002 Sep 9 (Box 685, Folder 8)
  - Memorial guest book (Box 685, Folder 9)
  - Memorial from the World Trade Center (WTC) Relief Organization (Box 685, Folder 10)
  - Memorial - An Expression of Deepest Sympathy - N.Y. Firefighters Burn Center Foundation (Box 685, Folder 11)
  - Memorial - In Tribute to Stephen Jay Gould - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS) (Box 685, Folder 12)
  - Trunk inventory (Box 923, Folder 12)
- Series 20. Family
  Materials in this series primarily relate to Gould's maternal and paternal grandparents, his father and mother, his brother Peter, his first wife Deb, his children Ethan and Jesse, and his efforts to chronicle his genealogy. Materials are arranged by family member.
  Files containing family medical and legal information closed for research until 2086.
  - Joseph and Irene Rosenberg (Box 663, Folder 1)
  - Samuel Gold (Box 663, Folder 2)
  - Leonard Gould (2 folders)
  - Leonard Gould - Activism (Box 663, Folder 5)
  - Leonard Gould - Activism - April 1953 Vet's Voice suppression (2 folders), 1953 Apr
  - Leonard Gould - Activism - Cartoons (Box 689, Folder 3)
  - Leonard Gould - Activism - FBI file on Leo Gould, 1968 (Box 663, Folder 6)
  - Leonard Gould - Activism - The Federation Reporter (Box 663, Folder 7)
  - Leonard Gould - Activism - NAACP (Box 663, Folder 8)
  - Leonard Gould - Activism - Servicemen's Defense Committee (Box 663, Folder 9)
  - Leonard Gould - Activism - Vet's Voice (Box 663, Folder 10)
  - Leonard Gould - Activism - Vet's Voice (Box 664, Folder 1)
  - Leonard Gould - Activism - Miscellaneous (Box 689, Folder 6)
  - Leonard Gould - Activism - Miscellaneous (3 folders) (Box 664-2, Folder 664-4)
  - Leonard Gould - Campaign re Adolph H. Schultz [anthropology and race] (3 folders)
  - Leonard Gould - Freedom of Information Act, FBI (Box 664, Folder 8)
  - Leonard Gould - Navy, WWII (Box 664, Folder 9)
  - Leonard Gould - Vet's Voice (Box 910)
  - Leonard Gould - WWII - Clippings (Box 689, Folder 8)
  - Eleanor Gould (Box 665, Folder 1)
  - Eleanor Gould - Owls (Box 689, Folder 7)
  - Eleanor Gould - Owls (4 folders)
  - Eleanor Gould - Owl scrapbook (Box 908)
  - Leonard and Eleanor Gold [Gould] - Name change to Leonard and Eleanor Gould (Box 664, Folder 12)
  - Leonard and Eleanor Gold [Gould] - Wedding, 1939 (Box 664, Folder 11)
  - Leonard and Eleanor Gould - Correspondence (Box 664, Folder 10)
  - Peter Gould - Correspondence (Box 667, Folder 3)
  - Peter Gould - Juvenilia (Box 667, Folder 4)
  - Peter Gould - Obituaries and rememberances (Box 667, Folder 5)
  - Deb Gould (2 folders)
  - Deb Gould - Correspondence (Box 665, Folder 8)
  - Deb and Steve Gould - Incoming postcards (Box 923, Folder 14)
  - Ethan Gould (Box 666, Folder 1)
  - Ethan and Steve Gould - Travel log (Box 666, Folder 2)
  - Ethan and Jesse Gould - Letters to Gould (Box 666, Folder 3)
  - Ethan and Jesse Gould - Drawings (Box 667, Folder 2)
  - Ethan and Jesse Gould - Holiday artwork (Box 667, Folder 10)
  - Jesse Gould (Box 923, Folder 16)
  - Jesse Gould (Box 666, Folder 4)
  - Jesse Gould - Correspondence (Box 666, Folder 5)
  - Jesse Gould - Violin recitals (3 folders)
  - Jesse Gould - Violin recitals (Box 667, Folder 1)
  - Jesse Gould - Incoming postcards (Box 923, Folder 15)
  - Jesse Gould - Family photographs (Box 923, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence with extended family (Box 667, Folder 6)
  - Family recipes (Box 667, Folder 11)
  - Genealogy - Family Chronicle (notebook), 1974 (Box 667, Folder 7)
  - Genealogy - Gould's family history, For Jesse and Ethan, 1976 (Box 667, Folder 8)
  - Genealogy (Box 667, Folder 9)
  - Vaccination records (Box 667, Folder 12)
  - Steve and Rhonda's wedding, 1996 (Box 667, Folder 13)
- Series 21. Works by others
  This series contains Gould's holdings of manuscripts, reprints, and other published writings by others. This series is divided into four subseries:
  Reprints by others. Many are boxed in cartons and are not described in detail. Those arranged by subject remain as ordered by Gould.
  Non-Gould publications. This subseries includes magazines, journals, catalogs, and newsletters Gould collected. Approximately half of these publications are grouped by title; the remainder are not described in detail.
  Manuscripts by others. This subseries is comprised primarily of unsolicited manuscripts sent to Gould for review and is arranged in alphabetical order by first letter of author's last name. Also included are thesis proposals and dissertations, also arranged in alphabetical order by first letter of author's last name.
  Journal peer reviews. Contains anonymous or blind pre-publication reviews for articles submitted to scholarly journals. This series is closed for research until 2086.
  - Subseries 1. Reprints by others
    - Reprints by others (Box 242)
    - Reprints by others (Box 246)
    - Reprints by others (Box 306)
    - Reprints by others (Box 339)
    - Reprints by others
    - Reprints by others (Box 369)
    - Reprints by others (Box 477)
    - Reprints by others (Box 489)
    - Reprints by others (Box 556)
    - Reprints by others (Box 559)
    - Reprints by others (Box 603)
    - Reprints by others (Box 680)
    - Reprints by others (Box 697, Folder 19)
    - Reprints by others - Arranged by subject (Allometry 2 I-L; Allometry 3 M-Q; Allometry 4 R-Z) (Box 261)
    - Reprints by others - Arranged by subject (Allometry 7; Allometry 8; Unlabeled) (Box 269)
    - Reprints by others - Arranged by subject (Allometry 1 A-H; Allometry 5; Biometrics 1) (Box 270)
    - Reprints by others - Arranged by subject (Biometrics 2; Biometrics 3; Biometrics 4) (Box 271)
    - Reprints by others - Arranged by subject (Biometrics 5; Form 1 A-H; Form 2 I-P) (Box 272)
    - Reprints by others - Arranged by subject (Form 3 Q-Z; Scale 2 O-Z; Unlabeled) (Box 273)
    - Reprints by others - Arranged by subject (Ontogeny 1; Ontogeny 2; Functional Morphology) (Box 274)
    - Reprints by others - Arranged by subject (Functional Morphology 2; Biometrics 6; Scale 1 A-N) (Box 275)
    - Reprints by others - Arranged by subject (Book 1; History of Science 1; History of Science 2) (Box 276)
    - Reprints by others - Arranged by subject (History of Science 3; History of Science 4; Philosophy of Science 1) (Box 277)
    - Reprints by others - Arranged by subject (Philosophy of Science 2; Book 2; Continental Drift) (Box 278)
    - Reprints by others - Arranged by subject (Diversity 1; Problematica; Origin 1, Pre-Cambrian) (Box 279)
    - Reprints by others - Arranged by subject (Origin 2, Pre-Cambrian; Ecology 1 A-H; Ecology 2 I-Z) (Box 280)
    - Reprints by others - Arranged by subject (Taxonomy; Adaptation 1; Macro-Evolution 1) (Box 281)
    - Reprints by others - Arranged by subject (Behavior 1; Speciation 1; Trigoniidae 1) (Box 282)
    - Reprints by others - Arranged by subject (Land Molluscs 1; Land Molluscs 2 L-Z; Marine Molluscs 2) (Box 283)
    - Reprints by others - Arranged by subject (Land Molluscs 1; Gilmore, Hay, Troxell) (Box 284)
    - Reprints by others - Arranged by subject (H.E. Crampton; L. Dollo; Memorials 1) (Box 285)
    - Reprints by others - Arranged by subject (Resources Politics 1; R.T. Jackson; Unlabeled) (Box 286)
    - Reprints by others - Arranged by subject (W.K. Gregory; Van Valen 1) (Box 287)
    - Reprints by others - Arranged by subject (Cerion; Punctuated Equilibrium) (Box 310)
    - Reprints by others - Cerion (Box 691, Folder 11)
    - Reprints - H. F. Osborn (5 folders)
    - Reprints - H. F. Osborn (2 folders)
    - Reprints - Pleistocene, West Indies (4 folders)
  - Subseries 2. Non-Gould publications
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) (Box 241)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) (Box 268)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) (Box 294)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) (Box 311)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) (Box 320)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) (Box 337)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) (Box 338)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) (Box 341)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) (Box 346)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) (Box 351)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) (Box 437)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) (Box 456)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) (Box 486)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) (Box 526)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) (Box 532)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) (Box 602)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) (Box 659)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) (Box 557)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) - AAPG Bulletin, 1974-1976 (Box 535)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) - AAPG Bulletin, 1976-1977 (Box 536)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) - The American Association of Petroleum Geologists Bulletin, 1959-1967 (Box 494)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) - The American Association of Petroleum Geologists Bulletin and The Popular Science Monthly, 1967-1969, 1901-1914 (Box 495)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) - Discover, 1985 Sep-1992 Mar (Box 474)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) - Discover, 1992 May-1996 Mar (Box 475)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) - Discover, 1996 Apr-1998 Feb (Box 476)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) - Discover, 1998-2001 (Box 473)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) - Discover and Wetenschap Cultuur En Samenleving, 1982-1998 (Box 493)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) - Evolution, 1950-1965 (Box 453)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) - Evolution, 1966-1975 (Box 454)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) - Evolution, 1976-1977 (Box 455)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) - Evolution and AAPG Bulletin, 1947-1977 (Box 496)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) - KOS, FMR, Sfera, The Sciences (New York Academy of Sciences) (Box 497)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) - Natural History Magazine, Airone and miscellaneous publications, 1984-2001 (Box 492)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) - New Scientist, 1978-1982 (Box 513)
    - Non-Gould publications (journals, catalogs, newsletters) - Science, Nature and Discover, 1982-2002 (Box 533)
  - Subseries 3. Manuscripts by others
    - Manuscripts by others (various titles by Allan O. Kelly) (Box 243)
    - Manuscripts by others (Box 251-257)
    - Manuscripts by others (Box 298-300)
    - Manuscripts by others (Box 340)
    - Manuscripts by others (6 folders)
    - Manuscripts by others, A-B (20 folders)
    - Manuscripts by others, C-F (13 folders)
    - Manuscripts by others, F-H (21 folders)
    - Manuscripts by others, H-K (20 folders)
    - Manuscripts by others, K-L (13 folders)
    - Manuscripts by others, L-M (14 folders)
    - Manuscripts by others, M-P (16 folders)
    - Manuscripts by others, P-S (16 folders)
    - Manuscripts by others, S (15 folders)
    - Manuscripts by others, T-W (17 folders)
    - Manuscripts by others, W-Z and authors unknown (27 folders)
    - Manuscripts by others: The Last Dinosaur Book, by W.J.T. Mitchell, proof (Box 436, Folder 5)
    - Manuscripts by others: Mutter Museum, by Gretchen Worden, proof (Box 436, Folder 6)
    - Theses, thesis proposals and dissertations, A-I (3 volumes) (Box 443)
    - Theses, thesis proposals and dissertations, F (Box 658, Folder 14)
    - Theses, thesis proposals and dissertations, G (Box 658, Folder 15)
    - Theses, thesis proposals and dissertations, L (Box 658, Folder 16)
    - Theses, thesis proposals and dissertations, J-L (4 volumes) (Box 444)
    - Theses, thesis proposals and dissertations, L-Z (3 volumes) (Box 590)
- Series 22. Oversize (miscellaneous)
  This series contains large format print materials including artwork created by Gould's family members and others, maps, and various posters from events Gould participated in as well as non-Gould related events. Items are alphabetized by format.
  - Agassiz picture and letter (Box 584, Folder 3)
  - Artwork (Folder 3)
  - Artwork by children (Box 586, Folder 1)
  - Artwork by Gould's children (Box 584, Folder 1)
  - Artwork, owls (Box 584, Folder 4)
  - Artwork, miscellaneous (Box 516, Folder 1)
  - Artwork, miscellaneous (Box 586, Folder 9)
  - Artwork, miscellaneous (Box 438, Folder 9)
  - Artwork, miscellaneous (Box 584, Folder 5)
  - Artwork, miscellaneous (Box 585, Folder 1)
  - Artwork, miscellaneous (Box 583, Folder 3)
  - Artwork, miscellaneous (Box 583, Folder 4)
  - Artwork, miscellanous (Folder 10)
  - Calendars - American Museum of Natural History Calendar with an introduction by Gould and photographs by Rosamond Purcell; 25th Anniversary of the Cuban Revolution (Box 518, Folder 1)
  - Drawings (Box 515, Folder 10)
  - Drawings and pictures of Gould (Box 585, Folder 6)
  - Gould Memorial from the Uniformed Fire Officers Association (Box 586, Folder 8)
  - Gravestone etching (Box 911, Folder 1)
  - Maps (Box 516, Folder 2)
  - Maps (Box 586, Folder 12)
  - Maps (Folder 13)
  - Posters - Alexis Rockman (Folder 6)
  - Posters - Social Activism, miscellaneous (Box 518, Folder 9)
  - Posters - Social Activism, protest posters (Folder 7)
  - Posters - Tests (Folder 4)
  - Posters, miscellaneous (Box 516, Folder 3)
  - Posters, miscellaneous (Box 518, Folder 10)
  - Posters, miscellaneous (Box 584, Folder 6)
  - Posters, miscellaneous (Box 586, Folder 13)
  - Posters, miscellaneous (Folder 12)
  - Posters, miscellaneous, including evolution related iconography (Folder 2)